## Kiran Deshmukh

Database Operations, Team Lead (Oracle, Postgres and Hadoop)

## Summary

#### **Experience Summary**

Kiran has proven leadership, achiever, and activator, analytical, arranger, self-driven professional. He has the ability to analyze problems, develop solutions, build consensus programs and bring program/project execution to completion. He is recognized for his contributions, deep commitments and passion for building, a best service provider. He has a experience in development and implementation of various projects in ERP, Telecom, Finance suite and also using ETL tools and client server applications.

Overall 24 years of IT experience of which 20 years of experience in Oracle Database Administration. Being a DBA Lead - Subject Matter Expert / DB Operations Manager accountable for systems running on Oracle Server with multi-million USD Remote Infrastructure Management Systems, Primary responsibility is to ensure smooth Operations to Vodafone client on 24x7x365 basis, and responsible for profit and loss of the accounts. Managing and monitoring Incident, Change and Problem Management in line with ITIL Framework. Conduct monthly service reviews and develop relationships and manage proactively senior level stakeholder expectations and demands.

Demonstrated high competency in the planning and execution of 24x7 SLA based support for mission critical database environments; ability to lead projects and project team members to successful goal achievement.

#### Expertise/ Specialization

Customer Focus: Understand the clients' businesses, needs and goals from their point of view, build long-term relationships, anticipate needs and respond appropriately to their concerns and problems. Display commitment to client value.

Capacity Planning & management: Evaluation of DB hosting environment with Trend analysis, Modeling, Bench-marking.

#### Technologies:

Oracle8/9/10/11/12,

Hadoop, Postgres, casendra, Hive, HBase, Pig,

MangoDB, Sqoop, Amezon cloud.

## Experience

# Database Operations, Team Lead (Oracle, Hadoop, Postgres) at IBM October 2012 - Present

- Demonstrated managing a wide variety of issues
- Strong communication and strong collaboration skills
- Experience with multiple database platforms (Oracle, MySQL, MSSQI, DB2, Hadoop)
- Strong troubleshooting and problem solving skills
- Managing production database servers
- · Passionate for learning and using new technologies
- · Thrives in a fast-paced, innovative environment
- Providing production database support for nearly 600 nos 24x7
- Participate in the design and documentation of technical standards and best practices
- Deliver technical and administrative assistance to my team members
- Lead and take ownership and team managment
- Provide Oracle database technical training and mentor team members
- Interview candidates to assess the recruiting team in decision taking
- Participate in the development or enhancement of administrative and technical processes
- Represent my team in internal and external Sarbanes Oxley audits
- Be the technical escalation contact for the primary on call member
- Managing the oracle databases for 10g / 11g/ 12 C in a 24\*7 production environment Databade Monitoring
- Database planning and creation
- Database Migration
- Backup & recovery on production setup
- Designed, tested and implemented Oracle high availability solutions
- Allocate storage and develop plans for future storage requirements
- SQL Tuning in an Oracle Environment
- Creation of physical and logical standby
- Managing the database in a data guard scenario with physical and logical standby databases
- Managing and monitoring the log apply services & log transport services
- RAC setup and configuration
- Create and administer real application cluster databases
- Managing the backup and recovery in RAC environment
- Upgrade, Migration, Patching, Cloning of Oracle RAC Database,
- Converting single instance databases to RAC
- Knowledge related to RAC guard architecture, components
- Installing & Configuring Oracle Clusterware & Oracle RAC.

Senior Databade Operations at R Systems International Ltd, Pune Maharastra. (Indus)

#### November 2008 - October 2012 (4 years)

- •Responsible for entire database activities and providing service to 50+ clients
- •Performed Remote Oracle DBA activities for several clients.
- •Hands on experience to handle technical escalations and also perform incident investigation and diagnosis
- •Design optimal disaster recovery utilizing Oracle Data Guard and Fast Start Failover
- •Create database maintenance plans, including installation, patch application, updating statistics, re indexing, structure modifications, high water mark check, data growth, alert errors/warnings, Capacity plans, and index analysis.
- •Installation and administration of oracle 9i/10g/11g Real application cluster (RAC) with shared storage ASM, network file system (NFS)
- Implement Oracle Data Guard, Streams and Oracle Golden Gate, Multi Master Replication
- Unix shell scripts as per requirements
- Extensive experience in SQL, PL/SQL, Query Optimization using optimizer hints, Explain plan, SQL trace, Auto trace, TKPROF, SQL Analyzer
- Experience in partitioning and sub-partitioning (Range, Hash, List, Composite) of tables in Data Warehouse, OLTP environment
- Storage Management Managing Space, Table spaces, Multi-tenant data, Partition tables, Global–Local Indexes, Segments, Extents & Data Dictionary.
- •Extensive experience of Installation and configuring Recovery Manager (RMAN) and Flash Recovery.
- •Hands on experience of over 30+ client's databases migrated from legacy system to new system successfully(9i to 10g/11g or 10g to 11g).
- Hands on experience to ETL
- Multi-tenant data design & virtualization technologies.
- Resolved development Teams doubt and issues related to databases
- Experience of deployment of product on Cloud platforms (Amazon AWS)
- High availability Architect by Database Golden Gate/Data Guard/Oracle Streams/Multi Master Replication
- Program Code Review and Document and improve existing processes

### Sr Manager at Kirloskar Oil Engines Ltd

November 2007 - June 2008 (8 months)

- Provided on demand remote DBA services
- Chief technologist for Oracle Application Release12 all modules custom Reports Development
- Handled 6 member team
- Manage risks and issues impacting project deliverables
- Primary interface to the customer, vendors and alliance personnel associated with the project
- Escalate relevant issues and risks in accordance to the TPD Project Issue and

Risk Management Procedure and the account specific Process

- Program Code Review
- Regular communication to management concerning a project's status, potential risks, concerns, problems and needs.
- Keep abreast of new design tools, hardware, software, and technology and make recommendations for future deployment.
- Held meetings with different departments and clients to assess their demands and documented them accordingly
- Arranged training programs and workshops for team members facing difficulty in project work
- Assisted other experts in completing the projects by sharing knowledge and experience gained from other projects
- Helped in performing audits and testing of newly completed projects
- Excellent problem solving skills
- Knowledge of Project Management Methodology and Scheduling

#### Group Leader

January 2006 - November 2007 (1 year 11 months)

- •Provided on demand on site and remote DBA services
- •Handle technical escalations and also perform incident investigation and diagnosis
- •Primary interface to the customer, vendors and alliance personnel associated with the project
- •In charge of deciding on hardware, scaling of tiers based on number of users & application
- Installed and configured oracle 9i/10g/11g databases on Dev/Test/Prod system
- Tuned more than 20+ databases and resulting in 40% overall performance
- Have deep knowledge of SQL, PL/SQL
- Installation and administration of oracle 9i/10g/11g Real application cluster (RAC) with shared storage ASM, network file system (NFS)
- Hands on experience in oracle 10g FLASHBACK to provide fast and easy recovery at data base, table, and row and transaction level
- Extensive experience in oracle 11g/10g AWR, ADDM, ASH to collects and maintains performance statistics for problem-detection and self-tuning purposes
- Experience in UNIX shell scripting, Window batch programming, Perl scripting, SSH, SCP
- Proficient in SQL, PL/SQL, Query Optimization using optimizer hints, Explain plan, SQL trace,
   Auto trace, TKPROF, SQL Analyzer
- Experience in partitioning and sub-partitioning (Range, Hash, List, Composite) of tables in Data Warehouse, OLTP environment
- Provided disaster recovery by configuring and maintaining physical standby database using oracle Data Guard
- Performed logical backup of database schemas, tables using Export/Import and data pump utility

- Performed, developed and maintained database backup and recovery using RMAN for various failures
- Granted and revoked privileges to users as per requests and maintained database security procedures
- Developed and implemented a comprehensive Disaster Recovery Plan for the Oracle Databases at the division.
- Resolved development Teams doubt and issues related to databases
- · Database creation, Tablespace Management, User Management, DB error handling

#### Dy Manager - IT at Piaggio Vehicles Pvt. Ltd.

January 2000 - January 2006 (6 years 1 month)

- Designed, developed Oracle based total in house ERP solution. The system had 5000 tables and 15000 stored procedures, among others.
- Served as DBA and Project Manager
- Managed 20+ Developers for development of ERP
- Conceptual, Logical and Physical modeling
- Define Entity, Relationship, Normalization
- Interface, Validation, Checks, procedures design
- Managed all aspects of the project business plan and budget.
- Managed the operational, financial and technological aspects of projects based on time-lines and work plans
- Identified resources requirement, assigned responsibilities and coordinated directly and indirectly project staff to ensure successful completion of the project.
- Tracked project deliveries using project management tools
- Reported on project progress and communicated relevant information to superiors.
- Resolved, traced and escalated critical issues to minimize project risk factors.
- Prepared the QA procedure of the project.
- Communicated intensively with clients, sub-contractors and vendors to establish cordial/effective working relationship.
- Followed up with clients to verify satisfaction
- Design of tables, indexes, primary & foreign keys
- Front End Design (Screen), Navigation & Validations
- Unit testing & bug fixing
- Technical team leads for the entire project life cycle to software engineers (5 engineers).
- In charge of deciding on hardware, scaling of tiers based on number of users & application
- Chief technologist for all database performance tuning and implementation
- Performed requirements & gap analysis.
- Migrated legacy data with over 4 million records to newly developed ERP
- Implemented Versioning system CSV to source code

- Provided post-production support and developed data extraction for downstream systems.
- Dealing with complex technical issues and to adapt in a team-based organization.
- Handled DBA responsibility at Development/SIT/UAT/Production

#### Asst. Manager (IT)

December 1997 - January 2000 (2 years 2 months)

Company Profile Manufacturing world-class seamless steel tubes & Dipes.

Environment Windows NT 4.0, Oracle 7.1, Developer/2000

#### Responsibilities

- · System Administration and Functional Administration.
- Designed and developed an information system covering all operational areas.
- Responsible as a Team Leader from the commencement of project.
- Performed logical database design, developed stored PL/SQL packages, forms and reports using Oracle Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5.
- Major Responsibilities in trouble shooting and debugging scripts.
- Performed application level tuning.
- Provided post-production support

#### Asst. Manager (IT)

October 1995 - November 1997 (2 years 2 months)

- System Administration and Functional Administration.
- Designed, Developed & Implemented in house ERP system
- Requirement Analysis
- Conceptual, Logical and Physical modeling
- Define Entity, Relationship, Normalization
- Interface, Validation, Checks, procedures design
- · Design of tables, indexes, primary & foreign keys
- Front End Design (Screen), Navigation & Validations
- System testing & bug fixing
- Technical team leads for the entire project life cycle to software engineers (5 engineers).
- In charge of deciding on hardware, scaling of tiers based on number of users & application
- Chief technologist for all database performance tuning and implementation
- Performed requirements & gap analysis.
- Responsible as a Team Leader from the commencement of project.
- Performed logical database design, developed stored PL/SQL packages, forms and reports using Oracle Forms 4.5, Reports 2.5.
- Major Responsibilities in trouble shooting and debugging scripts.
- Performed application level tuning.
- Provided post-production support

- Database Administration
- Held meetings with different departments and clients to assess their demands and documented them accordingly
- Arranged training programs and workshops for team members facing difficulty in project work
- Assisted other experts in completing the projects by sharing knowledge and experience gained from other projects
- Helped in performing audits and testing of newly completed projects

#### Asst. Systems Analyst

June 1994 - September 1995 (1 year 4 months)

Company Profile Manufacturing Push Buttons Telephone Sets

Environment Clipper 5.0

Responsibilities Systems specifications Study, Analysis and Design.

#### Programmer

June 1993 - June 1994 (1 year 1 month)

Company Profile Chartered Accounting firm having more then 1500 clients.

Environment Clipper 5.0

Responsibilities Programming

#### Programmer

May 1992 - May 1993 (1 year 1 month)

Company Profile Manufacturing of jecord towels, chaddars.

Environment Clipper 5.0

Responsibilities Programming

#### Education

#### Edureka

Hadoop Administrator, Hadoop Administrator, 2016 - 2016 Activities and Societies: Big Data, Hadoop Administrator

Certification to ITIL V3 Foundation

ITIL, ITIL V3 Foundation, 2011 - 2011

Activities and Societies: Certification to ITIL V3 Foundation

Certification to International Auditor

ISO 207001;2005, Certification to International Auditor ISO207001:2005), 2009 - 2009

Activities and Societies: Certification to International Auditor ISO207001:2005)

Certification to Linux

Database Administration, Oracle, 2007 - 2007

Activities and Societies: Seed Infotech, Pune: Certification to Linux (RH-33,RH-133)

Oracle Developer/2000

Workshop, Oracle Developer/2000, 2004 - 2004

Activities and Societies: Spider Systems Pvt Ltd: Training of Advanced to Developer/2000

Master of Computer Management

M.C.M., Master of Computer Management, 1991 - 1992 Activities and Societies: Bytco College, Nashik, Maharastra

PG Diploma in Computer Science PGDCS, PGDCS, 1989 - 1990

Activities and Societies: Walchand Institute of Engineering, Solapur

Bachalor of Science (Electronics)
B.Sc., B. Sc. Electonics, 1986 - 1989

Activities and Societies: Dayanand College, Solapur, Maharastra

**HSC** 

H.S.C., H.S.C., 1984 - 1986

Activities and Societies: Walchand College, Solapur, Maharastra

S.S.C.

S.S.C., 10th, 1983 - 1984

Activities and Societies: D. J. Gurukul High School, Solapur, Maharastrara

#### Honors and Awards

Parter Achiever Award, IBM Award

## Kiran Deshmukh

Database Operations, Team Lead (Oracle, Postgres and Hadoop)



Contact Kiran on LinkedIn